Schaefer, Vincent; Papers ua902.010
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
- Biographical & Autobiographical Materials, 1909-1993; Undated; 12; 13.5 cubic ft.
  - Dutch Barns, 1930-1993; Undated; 12.2
    - The Wemple/Dellamont Dutch Barn, Undated (Box 10 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 12)
    - "What is a Dutch Barn? An Opinion"- Vincent Schaefer, 1988 (Box 10 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 13)
    - Written Analysis- Photos and Maps of Dutch Barns in New York, Undated (Box 10 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 14)
  - Local History and Archeology, 1909-1993; Undated; 12.3
    This subseries features materials related to history in New York, especially near the Capital District, and archeological research, two of Vincent Schaefer's important personal interests. Schaefer was a vice president and trustee of the Schenectady County Historical Society and wrote for the organization's Milestone newsletter. He also helped found the Van Epps-Hartley chapter of the New York State Archeological Association, which was formally organized in 1931, and later served as chapter president. There is significant correspondence about the chapter's founding and several articles authored by Schaefer about archeological sites and artifacts in this subseries. There also is correspondence between Schaefer and New York State Archeologist Arthur C. Parker, then museum director at the City of Rochester, New York's Municipal Museum.
    - Adirondack History, 1986; 1989; 1992; Undated (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 1)
    - Albany County History, 1988 (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 2)
    - "A Little of the Story and Interests as Told by Old Military Buttons"- Robert M. Hartley, 1937 (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 3)
    - "The Amateur in the Field of Archeology"- VJ Schaefer, 1934 March 30 (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 4)
    - Annotated Map of Schenectady, Undated (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 5)
    - Archeological Miscellany, ca. 1993-1988 (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 6)
    - Archeological Research-Exploration-Lone Scout Publication, 1921-1924; 1992; Undated (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 7-9)
    - Archeological Sites Explored by Schaefer-Handwritten Manuscripts, Notes, Drawings, 1926-1927 (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 10)
    - Cave Life Manuscript and Photographs, Undated (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 11)
    - Christian Wildlife Sanctuary Trail, 1934 (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 12)
    - City of Rochester, New York's Municipal Museum-Rochester Museum of Arts and Sciences, 1940-1943; 1945; 1947 (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 13)
    - Eastern States Archeological Federation, 1934; 1937; 1944 (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 14)
    - Eastern States Archeological Federation-Meetings, 1935 (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 15)
    - Field of Archeology in New York State-Handwritten Report and Notes, Undated (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 16)
    - Field Studies and Notes, Undated (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 17)
    - Five Rivers Area, Undated (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 18)
    - The Formulation of a Tree Calendar in the Mohawk Valley-Vincent Schaefer, 1934 (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 19)
    - Fundamentals of Geology-Handwritten Notes, Undated (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 20)
    - General Correspondence, 1927-1983 (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 21)
    - General Correspondence, 1986-1991; Undated (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 22)
    - Glacial Lake Albany, 1989 (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 23)
    - Hand Drawn Maps and Diagrams, Undated (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 24)
    - "How to be a Fossil Maker"-Vincent Schaefer, 1947 (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 25)
    - Images of Archeological Objects, Undated (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 26)
    - Lake Champlain Tercentenary, 1909 July 04-1909 July 10 (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 27)
    - Lake George Institute of History, Art and Science, and Lake George Historical Association, 1964-1967; 1970-1976; Undated (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 28-29)
    - Land Surveys, Undated (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 30)
    - "Let's Find An Indian Arrowhead"-Vincent Schaefer, Undated (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 31)
    - *Living History*, Undated (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 32)
    - Mabie House, 1974 (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 33)
    - "Mohawks in the Lower Valley"-Vincent Schaefer, 1955 (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 34)
    - Mohawk Valley, 1934; 1938; 1946; 1952; Undated (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 35)
    - Montgomery County, Crater of Unknown Origin, 1943 (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 36)
    - Montgomery County History, Undated (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 37)
    - Montgomery Manor-Montgomery County, 1992-1993; Undated (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 38)
    - Negatives, Archeological and Historic Sites, 1928-1961; Undated (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 39)
    - New York State Archeological Association, Including *The Bulletin* and Constitution, 1940-1987; Undated (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 40-41)
    - News clips-Archeological and Historic Topics, 1933; 1936; 1979; Undated (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 42)
    - News clips-Schaefer Speaking Engagements on Archeological Topics and Van Epps-Hartley Chapter Activities, 1934; 1936; 1941; 1946 (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 43)
    - Owasco Aspect, Undated (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 44)
    - Painting of a Native American Woman- Ralph Tillman, 1947 (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 45)
    - Photo Album- Archeology and Nature Expeditions, 1920s (Oversized 10)
    - Photographs- Archeological and Historic Sites, 1936; 1952; Undated (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 46)
    - Photographs- Geological Sites, Undated (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 47)
    - Pottery Beach- Remnants of Old Fort Niskayuna, Undated (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 48)
    - Pre-Iroquoian Occupations of New York- Mentioning Turnbull, Van Orden, Schermerhorn, Vosburg, Undated (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 49)
    - Prehistoric Man in the Mohawk Region- Percy Van Epps, 1935 (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 50)
    - Saratoga County History, Undated (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 51)
    - Schenectady County History-Including *The Milestone* and VJ Schaefer Papers, 1909-1989; Undated (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 52)
    - Schenectady Museum, 1941; 1952; 1955 (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 53)
    - Schaefer- Notes on Expeditions about Archeology, Undated (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 54)
    - Schoharie County History, 1941-1987; Undated (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 55)
    - Slides- Archeological and Historic Sites, 1944-1988; Undated (Box 11 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 56)
    - Slides- New York Sites, 1964-1966; 1969; 1971; 1973 (Box 12 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 1)
    - Society for American Archeology Notebook, 1939-1942 (Box 12 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 2)
    - Survey of History and the Natural Sciences of the Five Rivers Area, 1936 (Box 12 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 3)
    - Turnbull Site, 1927; 1937; Undated (Box 12 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 4)
    - The Van-Epps Hartley Bulletin, 1936-1940 (Box 12 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 5)
    - Van Epps-Hartley Chapter-New York State Archeological Association, 1931-1959; Undated (Box 12 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 6)
    - Van Epps-Hartley Chapter Receipts, 1932-1935; Undated (Box 12 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 7)
    - "Van Orden Component-Hudsonian Aspect"- Vincent J. Schaefer, Undated (Box 12 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 8)
    - The Vosburg Site, 1988; Undated (Box 12 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 9)
    - Vroman's Nose- History, Undated (Box 12 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 10)
    - Vroman's Nose Preservation Corporation, 1988-1992 (Box 12 (12-Biographical & Autobiographical Materi), Folder 11)